This video is sponsored by blue.impact,
a non-profit providing free,
high-quality courses on the future of
technology. Begin their courses for free
using my link in the description.
If you're around your mid-20s or older,
odds are very high that at some point in
elementary school, you learned how to
write cursive. You were required to to
dedicate a meaningful amount of time,
effort, and perhaps stress to learning
the shapes of each letter, the way each
connects to the [music] next, and how to
bring the end of a pencil or pen to
create them efficiently and effectively.
And you were graded [music]
on this ability.
Odds are also extremely high that
[music] since then, you've almost never
needed to know how to write cursive.
Outside of the process of learning it,
and perhaps your signature, it was
essentially all for nothing. And even
signatures now are mostly done
digitally.
Before computers, typewriters, and
ballpoint pens, cursive made sense as a
primary form of writing. Most of what
was written was written by hand, and
with early writing tools like dip pens
and fountain pens, cursive was the most
efficient and clean method, and became
the dominant form of handwriting.
Letters flowed together, and the
continuous strokes prevented the
blotting and scribbling that occurred
when lifting the pen. By the early and
mid-1900s, however, dip and fountain
pens were becoming less central as
typewriters and then ballpoint pens
became increasingly common. By 2006,
only 15% of students wrote in cursive
when given the option to write in either
cursive or print in the essay portion of
the SAT. In 2010, cursive was taken off
the Common Core standards in the US,
deemed no longer sufficiently relevant
to require teaching.
Computers were now being used to write
when pencils and pens weren't, and
pencils and pens didn't require any
special writing [music] style to
function well. Though cursive may be
somewhat faster for handwriting, it
certainly isn't faster or more efficient
than typing on a computer. And for
legibility and standardization,
computers use print.
Though there are are potential fine
motor skills and hand-eye benefits to
learning cursive. It isn't obvious how
much more, if any, compared to just
learning how to write in print. And
although there is perhaps some nostalgic
and niche value to writing and reading
cursive, broadly speaking, there aren't
any real obvious universal reasons to
compel all students to learn and be
graded on it.
And yet, as of 2026, several US states
have signed new laws requiring school
districts to teach cursive writing in
elementary school. This comes after
several states throughout the 2010s also
passed bills that legislated
requirements for students to learn
cursive.
Of course, there's only so much time in
a day, in a year, in a childhood, in a
life. And so, why would states and
school districts [music] require
allocating time to something that is
ostensibly obsolete? Something that's
broad value is unclear and hasn't been
standard in decades.
A survey conducted in 2026 by Higher
Education Policy Institute reported that
94% of UK undergraduate students now use
generative AI in at least some part of
their assignments.
Interestingly, the survey also found
that many students will now actually be
encouraged or required to use AI in
assignments. Roughly 12% of students
report that they include AI-generated
text directly in coursework. Similarly,
a Harvard survey in 2024 led by AI
safety researcher Gabriel Woo found
similar numbers in the US, also noting
that 25% of students have begun to
substitute attending office hours and
course material with AI.
And so, at the exact same time, children
in elementary schools are being required
to learn cursive, while adults in
colleges are being required, or at least
expected, to use generative AI.
What could showcase more clearly the
confounding inability of the modern
world [music] to understand and keep up
with itself?
The more fundamentally interesting
question here, arguably, isn't whether
the requirement of cursive in elementary
school or the use of AI in academia is
right or wrong, good or bad. The
interesting question is, how do
educational systems and institutions
evaluate what they allow, teach, and
incentivize? [music]
What should education prioritize, and
how does its priorities and incentives
affect the kinds of humans it helps
form, and the subsequent society those
humans help form?
We become what we behold. We shape our
tools, and then our tools shape us.
Said American academic John Culkin.
Right now, the ability to use and
interface with digital technologies like
AI is becoming, if not already, central
to careers and many aspects of society
and life. And yet, it's unclear why the
use of many of these technologies in a
student's education [music] wouldn't be
considered cheating based on most
pre-existing understandings. But so too
are calculators, search engines, spell
check, and typing itself. And so,
particularly in the modern world,
technologies can simultaneously be a
form of cheating in education, while
also being central to life outside it.
What kinds of thinking and expression
should actually matter and be
prioritized then, and why?
In a valley in Argentina, there's a cave
known as the Cueva de las Manos, or the
Cave of the Hands.
Inside are walls covered with diverse
ancient paintings.
The cave derives [music] its name from
one of the most interesting and
affecting of the kinds of paintings
known as negative hand stencils.
Across the various sections of the cave,
there are nearly 900 hands, each created
by an individual human pressing their
hand up against the wall and blowing
pigment against it. Similar hand
stencils have been discovered in various
ancient caves across the world, from
France
>> [music]
>> to Spain to Indonesia to Australia to
Africa and more.
Most of these hand paintings are
estimated to be anywhere from 10 [music]
to 40,000 years old. We don't know
exactly why these paintings were made or
what meaning they might have had to the
various ancient groups and tribes who
painted them, who, interestingly, never
would have come in contact with each
other. But we do know that each painting
was created by a human hand and [music]
a human mind. We know that they are each
distinct markers of a clear humanity. A
humanity that seems [music] to need to
create, to coordinate, to symbolize, and
showcase itself on the walls of
eternity.
Without a single word, these handprints
[music] say,
"I was here.
I was human.
I know of a self and a future.
I care about a self and a future."
Each of our hands, right now, tens of
thousands of years later, would look no
different on that wall if sprayed with
the same pigment. The bodies and minds
through which we experience reality have
remained mostly the same as our
Paleolithic ancestors.
And yet, our daily realities are
incomprehensibly different. As we have
progressed through time and technology,
through civilization and culture, our
hands have remained the same, but they
are less and less present [music] in
what we do and express.
We are still ourselves, but less of
ourselves are needed. This isn't
necessarily a bad or a good thing.
>> [music]
>> Like all things, it is both and neither.
"Every technology," wrote author and
theorist Neil [music] Postman, "is both
a burden and a blessing. Not either or,
but this and that." [music]
But, the question certainly remains,
does it matter and how much when things
like communication and art
>> [music]
>> contain less and less of a visible human
being?
We have gone from hand stencils and
paintings on cave walls to handwritten
stylistic lettering to hand-typed pages
to AI-generated text [music] and images.
With each shift, the hand is needed less
and less, seen less and less.
And now, in many ways, the mind, [music]
too.
Eventually, hopefully, we will be the
ancient people looked back upon by
confused humans not so dissimilar from
us.
>> [music]
>> And when they look upon our art, our
creations, our forms of communicating
and being,
what will they see?
What will they feel?
Will they recognize us?
Will it be the same humanity we see when
we look into the cave of hands,
or will they see something different?
A new kind of negative stencil
>> [music]
>> of a new kind of humanity.
We have seemingly pressed our psyches
against the wall of the future and
sprayed them with digital pigments. It's
entirely unclear what those stencils
will look like in time. It's impossible
to even imagine, but it is possible to
help determine their shapes and colors.
It is possible to work to preserve what
we care about
because what we care about is what we
will become.
I had just recently finished writing the
essay for this video when I was reached
out to by an incredible nonprofit that's
providing free resources that overlap
with many of these same topics,
questions, concerns, and goals. They're
called Blue Dot Impact and their mission
is to help ensure the future of
technology and AI go well for humanity
and they've been kind [music] enough to
sponsor this video. I personally find AI
simultaneously incredibly fascinating
and awe-inspiring while incredibly
overwhelming and concerning. I know I'm
not unique in feeling this tension and
confusion. Most of the media coverage
and conversations around AI are either
baseless hype or baseless doom.
Very little of it actually helps you
understand what's going on, let alone
meaningfully participate. Last year
alone, Amazon, Google, Meta, and
Microsoft spent over $400 billion
building AI infrastructure. For
reference, the entire Apollo space
program, adjusted for inflation, spent
around $280 billion. So, current annual
AI spending is equivalent to multiple
missions to the moon. Only in the case
of AI, we don't really know where we're
going.
Part of the future being uncertain also
means it isn't fixed and determined.
[music] It is and will continue to be
shaped by those working in and around
the space. Through high-quality
comprehensive courses, Blue Dot helps
you become more informed about AI so you
can become more involved in shaping it
and the future, whether through
engineering and computer science or how
it's governed through policy and law or
by helping parse and share information.
And all their courses are completely
free. No premium tiers and no upsells.
You can get started today through the
link in my description.
Thousands have already gone through
their courses, many of which are now
working at some of the largest companies
and government organizations in the
world making technology better for
humanity.
And of course, as always, thank you so
much for watching in general. And see
you
next video.